And in your decision to trade back three
times, can you maybe put into
perspective patience
um but at a time when there was a little
bit of a sense of urgency with the
change and transitioning and want to win
and the whole thing, but how do you
balance one and the other? Yeah, I mean
Tim, we we really I tell you every year
we try to read our board and you know I
I think I was trying to allude to it in
here last week with the pre-draft
presser that
you know we didn't have a heavy number
of first round grades and so once we saw
the last player come off our board that
we had a first round grade on, you know,
we started being more aggressive with
the calls And we had some different
opportunities to go back further at one
time, but we also wanted to kind of see
how things fail before we before we did
it. And we felt like there was still
going to be interest by doing that. And
I looked at it. It's it's luck. It's not
skill. But um we were considering a move
with from 26 all the way into two that I
thought was a good move for us
in the end. And then when we did the one
to 28, I'm like, well, this is this is
good, but you're also thinking, man, I
really could have done a lot. Where I'm
going with that is in the end by the
multiple trades we ended up with more
than that in a very similar position. So
some of that's good fortune those teams
still wanted to move back into one. Um
and it was just really following our
board. We had enough guys uh in a
similar value on the board that we felt
confident going to 35
we would be able to get a player like
TJ. There were a lot of edge rushers in
that part of the draft. Brandon, why was
TJ the the one that you guys identified
as the fit for your defense?
>> Yeah, it was uh it was one of the
strengths of this draft. Uh was a
variety of edge rushers. Some of them
are more DPRish. Um I would say TJ is a
three down player. Uh his his sack
production a year ago was 11 11 and a
half, can't remember. uh sacks this
year, not as many. Um but you've seen
you saw enough from them. You know, we
did a long study of a lot of these guys
of two years versus just the one year.
Some guys were better this year, some
guys were better the previous year. We
also a guy like him had a really good
week at the Senior Bowl. So, we we try
and weigh it all. Um but it's it's some
close discussions, but you saw a run on
those guys today. you know, all those
guys were in a similar vein and that
gave us the confidence to move back
here. When I went home last night, I
felt confident we were going to add um
some type of rusher, whether it was a
three down, whether it was a a DPR type
um and TJ was the guy, you know, we had
number one if it if it fell that way.
>> Do you feel that um
>> player just taking?
>> Yeah.
>> Um is you you talked about Christian
Benford. I think that's interesting the
other day about where he projects maybe.
Um what kind of versatility does he
have? Is he strictly an outside corner?
What can he do for you?
>> Yeah, this guy uh IGB because he's got a
tougher name to say. Um obviously play
major competition uh at Ohio State. He
really, you know, a year ago did have
some penalties, but this year really
cleaned it up. Uh he's big, he's long.
You know, if you look at our two, you
know, kind of pencil in starters of
Benford and Max right now, those are two
different skill sets. I think this is a
third skill set, a big long The best
thing he does is press. Um, some guys
are man match, some guys are best in
off. Um, I think he gives us another
added um, skill set. He started a lot of
games, you know, in major college
football. Um, he is wired the right way.
We brought him I went to his proday and
just I wanted to watch his movement, his
off the ball, you know, movement versus
just just press because he did so much
press at Ohio State. Um and you know, he
checked the box and and the multitude of
people that I talked to there just raved
about his football character, um his
competitiveness, his love of ball, great
teammate. uh and we found that out here
start you know Jordan Hancock you know
is close with him raved about him and so
those guys hung out when he came in for
a 30 visit as well so he kind of passed
all the all the test for us and you know
corner is a is a premium position you
you can't have enough of those guys and
and so right now with you know Tradavius
being a free agent um with Dorian's
uncertainty at this point we're we're
hopeful uh but you know, we have to
prepare right now, you know, with with
what we're working with and and this
adds another guy. You saw the depth of
our corners tested last year through
injury. And so, um, you want to make
sure as the season goes along, if injury
strikes that you got enough guys, even
if they're not starters. So, this is a
depth player that'll come in and
compete. He'll push, you know, our
starters in time and and um, you know,
we'll kind of take it one day at a time.
How did he take those convers How did he
take those conversations of those guys
being the pencled in starters just like
that he'll be a backup?
>> Oh, we don't we we haven't talked about
that. No, we haven't. No, I'm just He's
a rookie. So, I'm just like Max has been
here a year. CB's obviously, you know,
been here forever. So, any any rookie is
going to have to come in here and earn
it. Whether it's TJ, IGB, um whoever
else we select. I mean, if he's the best
player, he, you know, he'll start at the
best the best 11. We'll go out there.
But there's not really a discussion.
Discussion is come in here with all
these guys, learn our system, learn your
role, play special teams. I think he has
the demeanor, the makeup, the size to
also help on fourth down. Those are the
things you consider as you move into the
move down the draft and and add depth at
various positions. That's right. And he
had a lot of penalties called against
him, whether that's officiating or
technique, but is it a worry that he
committed so many penalties college?
>> Well, I would say S. Uh, good question.
One that we looked at. Um, he improved
those dramatically this year. And so,
we'll we'll work on that. Sometimes
that's technique. I'm not going to get
into the officiating of whether it was
I'm I'm going to assume they were they
were the good cause. You probably got
away with some that could have been
called and maybe were called for some
ticky tack. that usually evens out. Um,
that's one of the things that I would
say he improved the most. If you watch
his 24 film to his 25 film, very aware,
football smart,
um, young man, football savvy, you know,
he's probably, you know, off coverage is
something he'll have to continue to
improve on. I think more of those were
in that than than when he's up in press.
How how much would Jim Leonard have
known him or been aware of him when he
was at Wisconsin? And um in in the
overall picture in making the switch to
an attacking style of defense that Joe
Watts and Jim wants, how much was it how
how important was it to add pieces to it
today? Yeah, you know, we we felt like
listen, we want to add good players on
either side of the ball and and that'll
be the plan, you know, assuming we don't
pick any more tonight, tomorrow with
with what we have left. Um, but we did
feel like going into this draft after
free agency, you know, we added a DJ
Moore, we filled some of the holes in
the O line, we probably had more open
spots. Um I mean as you sit here today
with with I said who who was going to be
our third corner if we lined up and
played right now that's a again that's a
premium position. Um you know we lost
Ryan Vandymark. We got some guys who's
going to be our third tackle. Um you
know we got some guys here at least that
have you know in in Greyel and we
drafted Lunt last year. But it's
positions like that that you have to
make sure you're ready because look at
the game in I'm going back to the other
side of the ball. The Pittsburgh game
last year where two backup guys had to
start for us at tackle. So the same
thing at corner. We've got some probably
more available spots on defense than we
do on offense. So that's the other
conversation you're having as you move
down the board. How does the guy make
your roster? And if you feel good, he
makes your roster. Now, does he get a
jersey on game day? How does he does he
have fourth down value if he's not going
to be a starter? So, those will continue
to be the conversations tomorrow as we
work through the fourth and fifth round.
>> So, I uh I you'd have to ask Jim
directly. I don't remember. Jim was very
aware him and Jay Valai
um and Terrence Jameson uh along the
Dline, Bobby April, a lot on our
defensive staff have been around these
guys or recruited them. So there was a
lot of awareness uh of a number. I don't
remember specifically IGB without asking
Jim.
>> And you mentioned liking the uh depth at
edge rusher. So, I guess the flip side
to that would be why not wait at that
position if you feel like the depth is
there uh and address it later. What what
about TJ stood out that you felt like
you needed to to make that move then?
>> Yeah, you don't know how I mean there
was a run of them and you still have
them,
you know, you have guys in the second
round, guys. I do think if if if there
was a guy standing out above these guys,
it would have gave us some comfort that
we could get a player maybe, you know,
at this pick that we just took IGB
there. There's still some guys on the
board, but I do feel like, you know,
there was you're starting, you know,
those are lower on our board, so you you
kind of value them. I think with TJ, as
I said earlier, some guys are two down
players. They're they're run, some guys
are DPR. feel like TJ has proven over
the last couple years to be a three down
uh he brings a three down skill set, you
know, to the group and and I just think
that adds more value.
>> How do you evaluate whether this
strategy was worth passing on higher
drafted guys?
>> What's the question?
>> How how would you evaluate this strategy
was worth passing up on higher drafted
prospects?
>> Well, I'm basing on my board, so you
know, when you trade down, people are
going to go up. But that doesn't mean
just because someone's drafted there
doesn't mean that you valued them. Every
team has their own value and it doesn't
make them bad picks. Time will tell on
all these picks, right? But that's where
you you build your board. You study it
and you say, "Listen, in this case, we
had a number of players at a similar
value to TJ that we felt confident
moving back." And listen, time will
tell. TJ has to prove his worth of of
this pick. Uh just like IGB and whoever
else we select.
>> Did you come to trading up
>> uh in today?
>> Yesterday.
>> Uh yesterday. Um it didn't get close
enough when where I felt because knowing
that we didn't have the second round the
91st pick, you know, you you can go up
four or five maybe. I can't remember or
pair that with a four. You know, we had
so many of these,
you know, what I think are available
spots that we need to fill depth, youth,
add some some youth in various spots to
this roster. Um, we kind of went in
saying even if a guy fell close to us
that we were like, man, I can't believe
this guy's here. We wouldn't we wouldn't
want to lose too much of of that ammo.
So, it kind of got answered
fairly fast.
>> Point. How at what point do you have too
many picks? How how many guys how many
rookies can make this roster?
>> Yeah, it's uh great question and I think
we'll see as we go down, you know, the
board. And that's that's what we're
talking about with, you know, after this
pick of what other positions,
you know, do we do we know that if we
don't fill here in the draft, we
probably need to add some veteran
players after. But I still think there's
I still think we have some some spots
that we can fill tomorrow. Uh we did,
you know, part with one of the picks to
move up and and and make sure we got
IGB. So, uh what do we have? the three
fours, the two fives, and the seven. So,
yeah, I mean, you know, when you get to
the seventh round,
you know, for the most part, you're
you're kind of securing a guy that you
don't have to fight for as a priority
free agent. Um, so in my mind, we got
five picks. I would sit here and say
most likely, we'll see how the board
falls, Tim, but I would think a number
of these guys will have a chance to to
make a roster and help us In that plane,
how important was it to stockpile picks
on day one to give you some flexibility
to use as leverage to trade up at some
point? I mean, getting five picks in the
first 126, I think, was uh more than
double what you had going in.
>> Yesterday was was huge. How you know how
it worked out for us. And we knew when
we left here last night looking at the
board that we're going to be able to get
a rusher as I said and we thought, you
know, our board, you know, was stacked
and I think you saw it. I mean, you guys
can look at the picks in the second
round. It was a lot more defense than
offense. And we kind of saw that as well
and thought, you know, we'll follow it.
We're at 66. If we feel like a position
of need is is starting to thin out,
we'll move up. Not too far though
because
we worked hard to get get this
ammunition and we still feel there's
some some pieces that we would like to
add tomorrow that that can help this
team, you know, this year and going
forward.
>> Brandon, are you seeing when when you're
drafting defensive players and you did
the two tonight, um are you looking at
them differently for this particular
defense scheme versus what you've been
doing for the past nine years? and if
so, how?
>> Yeah, good question. It's probably
position specific a little bit, Vic. Um,
we're grading the, you know, we're
grading the player, the talent. Listen,
there were other corners. We weren't
just looking for a long press corner.
There were other corners that had that
were that were good as well that had a
little different skill set that we like.
So, it wasn't like Jim said, I need this
big long press corner. We put our values
on what they do well. um what are some
of the things they need to work on? S
referenced that you know the penalties
from a year ago. Uh the good thing was
that wasn't this year on that. But uh I
would just say position by position
obviously you know guys this is a this
is a three force are the guys that you
know used to be DNS for us. How do they
how do they stand up? You know are they
a SAM? Are they a rush? you know, so
that we probably spent more time on
those than we did, I would say, corners
and safeties. But I do think, you know,
there's been a little change even how we
exactly want our safeties before versus,
you know, what we can play with, you
know, under Jim's defense, how he would
utilize him. So, it was kind of position
specific more than anything. I know you
said that you after the last graded guy,
first round graded guy went off the
board. That's when you ultimately
decided to move down.
>> Yeah.
>> But you see the board thing out also as
it's going and you said that you knew
this was kind of a lesser year for first
round and you have eight minutes. So
when do you ultimately say to yourself,
is it leading up to the draft or at that
moment, hey, we got to start thinking
about maybe getting out of 26. Are you
really sitting there until that moment?
No, you're you have conversations even
before the draft starts with people
people calling do do you guys plan to
pick? Do you think you would move?
People in front of us calling, hey,
would you guys move up here? And you
know, teams that were, you know, five,
six, you know, however many up. It was
like, yeah, that's going to cost us too
much unless you're talking about giving
us some some great bargain, which, you
know, nobody's really going to probably
do in the first round. So, I would say
90% of our conversations were with the
teams directly behind us all the way
into the second round. Some of those
happen. Um I would say a lot of contact
is made just kind of setting parameters
of roughly what you might be talking
about for that pick. But like anything,
you know, yesterday a couple times some
teams were offering more and so you you
know it's like anything if more people
want it, you can charge a little more,
you know, on a premium of it. So it it
worked out on a couple of those deals.
We h we had a lot of interest in
26,
not as much in 28, but then we had a lot
in 30 was 31 the last. Yeah, we had a
lot in 31. Uh so
doing the move to 28 helps set up, you
know, the ammo that we got um there at
the end to move to 35. Brandon, why do
you feel comfortable using a good asset
like a second round pick on someone
who's least projected now be a backup
rather than addressing positions with
clear paths to instantly impact this
team?
>> Um I would say that will impact our
team. I mean, if you
if you look at the corners are premium
positions. If you just look at, you
know, who who makes the, you know, the
top dollars in the league. And if you
look at our season last year, and it's
it's happened before, John, those guys
are all going to play. They're going to
play. It's a long season. And when you
have corners that are not capable, they
get bullse eyes on them real fast. And
especially when you're playing the prime
time quarterbacks, the prime time
offenses in this league. I I can tell
you this, if there's another good corner
tomorrow, we'll take them. Like, think
of how many guys we went through last
season that played in the playoffs for
us or helping us get to the playoffs.
So, you're going to need those guys. And
again, you you're suiting up guys not
only to fill in as a backup, but also to
help you on fourth down, too. Those are
the kicking game matters as well.
>> Your advantage, what is the advantage on
having five picks in the top 25?
>> Yeah, you just, you know, you're you're
giving yourself, you know, a chance at
better players that you have on your
board, guys that you value the most. So,
uh, it's anytime you're adding assets,
it just gives you a chance to move up,
move down. You know, what we did
yesterday allowed us to be more
aggressive and take the six round pick
we had today to go secure a corner. I
know you didn't uh pay an exorbitant
price, but did you have an inkling that
a team between 62 and 65 might have been
looking at him or were you worried that
another team might be calling to move up
to get him?
>> I didn't I did know that some of those
teams were interested in moving back not
crazy far and
you know it's it's one of those
we we got enough ammo yesterday in a
spot like this where it's close it just
it just made too much sense. I was like,
would I rather sit here and wait or be
upset that the player was taken? It was
like, it's close enough. Let's just do
it.
>> I know you don't have a you don't have a
crystal ball. Like, you can't predict.
Like,
>> you guys don't think I have a crystal
ball,
>> right? Like, um, what's going to best
set up TJ for making an impact in year
one, but what have you learned as an
evaluator and about that part of the
process, figuring out how quickly they
can assimilate to your program? And do
you note that on your board for guys and
do they get kind of ratcheted up if
they're going to assimilate quicker?
>> Yeah, I mean we give what we've talked
about before, Bill's blue, which is guys
that have all the they can be a seventh
rounder, a first rounder, but they have
all the intangibles, great teammate.
They're going to work hard. They're
going to do everything they can to
achieve whatever the good Lord gave
them. Um, so that that is part of the
process. you know, we spend a lot of
time and and that's one of the things
that I've learned over my time here is
how important and it's it's ever
changing now with NIL the the athlete
you're getting and onboarding and the
pressure some of these guys are walking
in here with money that they didn't used
to walk in, you know, walk in here with.
Um, but they're still young men and
they're still working their way through
life. Sometimes they went to college
near where they went to high school and
this is the first time moving away from
home and they do hit challenges or
they're leaving their their fiance,
girlfriend, whatever they do life.
They're they're humans. I know a lot of
times we put them on pedestals, but that
is one of the things that we put a lot
of time and effort into our our player
engagement. Dr. Dez. Um, you know, we we
have a full hands-on deal trying to work
with these guys and try and onboard them
from college to being a professional.
How do you manage your hours? You don't
have class anymore. Um, you know, how do
you manage your week, nutrition, getting
them in our weight program? You know,
some of these guys are from smaller
schools. The weight program is totally
different. some of the guys, you know,
Ohio State probably not as big of a
different transition from their weight
program to ours, but sometimes you get
some some smaller school guys that are.
So, that is very important. And making
sure these guys are mentally and
physically right off the field helps you
get, you know, a better player on.
>> Brandon, how did you evaluate TJ's
attributes to rush the pass?
>> Yeah, I think he's I think he's got
speed, but I think he's got power. He
can use his arm. I think he's got a
multitude of of moves. I think there's
more in there. I think we can continue
to work on that. But, um, if you just
look at his athletic ability and you you
see it on tape, uh, I think again, as I
said, his his 24 film was very
impressive. It it really was. This year,
not as consistent. U, we'll, you know,
we'll talk about that. We'll look at
that. There were definitely flashes. You
and you saw it come up again at the end
of the year. uh against their rival
South Carolina. You saw it at a senior
bowl, so it's in there. We just got to
all those are part of maturity and uh
being a steady pro every day. You know,
we can't, you know, one year be this and
the next year be that. Um but the
flashes are are really good of a three
down player that will stick his face in
there and play the run, but you know, is
athletically explosive enough to help
you, you know, in the pass rush.
>> Differentiating
in this three four system who's going to
be on the outside like on the end on on
on the line and who's going to be on the
outside as far as linebackers go with
the players you have and what you need
to add
>> and then inside too.
>> Yeah. I mean like he's going to he'll be
a standup outside backer for us, you
know, like a like a chub type. That
would probably be his closest
comp on our team, you know, which will
be a great guy for him to learn from as
he moves forward. He he's also already
he's 21. He's already married. His dad
was a he's in the army and the Zoom call
he attributed a lot of his maturity
leadership to all of that. Can you kind
of take us through meeting with him and
those kind of characteristics?
>> Yeah, I mean I think that's uh as Matt
was talking about earlier like what are
you know he's for the most part has
shown to be a mature young man. I think
he got married during the by-week uh
last season. Comes from a military uh
family. So, you know, seems like he was
raised the right way. We, you know, we
have a scout here in Keith Jennings at
um played at Clemson, knows the Clemson
family pretty well. Pretty good insight
into this guy's daily routine, daily
work habits, and really felt like we
knew this this young man. Um, obviously,
you know, until you get him in your
building, you don't fully know him, but
um, you know, a guy that feels like he
is fairly mature for his age and we'll
we'll work together to kind of continue
to help him mature and welcome him and
his wife up here to Western New York.
>> 32. Was he a top 30?
>> No.
>> Is it?
>> You mentioned previously that you like
the depth at inside linebacker in this
class. There was a run on him in round
two. How do you feel about what could be
left on the board? Yeah, there's still
some guy there's still some guys, but
it's it's kind of like Jay's question
earlier. Um there's there's still guys,
but they're they're not as ranked as
necessarily as high as some of the guys
that that have already been taken. And
you understand that that means they
probably are deficient, you know, in an
area that that maybe somebody above them
was not, but there's still guys that can
help us. Um some guys better as line of
scrimmage players now may need work on
fourth down. And then there's some guys
vice versa. man, that guy is gonna
really Jeff Rogers is gonna love him,
but we we're gonna have some work to do,
you know, as you know, as one of our
backups, knowing that if they're going
to be suited up on game day, they have
to be able to, you know, kind of run the
defense.
>> I know it's not necessarily a premium
position, but when what went into the
decision to maybe not prioritize, you
know, inside linebacker, especially
scheme change and, you know, who you
have coming back?
>> We just followed the board. Yeah, we
would have if the if a backer was there
higher than Igmanos, we would have taken
him.
>> Brandon, the offseason addition of DJ
Moore, did that change the way you
looked at wide receiver even entering
the draft? And, you know, is there some
depth there that you may look to kind of
circle back to now as the picks? There's
depth there, but we look at it like we
selected DJ in the second round. And
that's truly he's an addition that we
did not have, you know, on this team
last year. And and so again, what I said
earlier, you're looking at, you know,
obviously his role, Shakir, um Palmer
coming back, Keon, we're, you know, and
it's not lip service like we're we're
excited about Keon and and he's, you
know, the first few weeks here. He's
it's been it's been very very positive
and I think you guys will see that in
time and and proud of what he's done.
But you know, Shavers is, you know,
rehabbing his knee. We got Micole
Hardman. We got a number of guys here.
So, you know, how do they get a jersey?
What's their role? You know, all those
factors, you know, to what to as we move
down the line on the board of receiver.
If it's the best player, though, we'll
definitely take it and throw them in the
mix and and let it shake, you know,
shake out how it does.
>> Why did you veer for more of an
all-around skill set with TJ versus
speed, more speed, explosiveness, bend
around the edge with some of the others?
Um, just you just evaluate the player.
It wasn't like we said, "Hey, we're
going for just speed or we're we weren't
not going for speed." I think I think TJ
I wouldn't say TJ's slow. TJ's a bigger
man than than you know, you know, maybe
an R. Mason, somebody like that. Um, two
different players, both very good
players. I mean, that another good pick
by Kansas City. Um, but it's you just
kind of put the players and you value
them how you do and and it doesn't mean
they're far apart or not. You just um,
as I said, he has a three down skill set
and and we like what what he brings.
>> You guys know strictly an outside
corner. Do you see any future? I
>> I mean, listen, I I would I would say,
you know, it would I don't see him
necessarily with a nickel skill set. I'm
not saying, you know, we we like
versatility. It's not that we would
never rep him there and see how he does.
Um I don't necessarily project that, you
know, from my lens as we sit there. I
see him more as an outside guy. Um but,
you know, obviously D offered is there.
Hancock's played nickel. You know, I
think we've we've got some guys that
that can do that role as well.
>> Brandon, you mentioned Trey being a free
agent with this and the value put on
corners. Is that door still open or how
do you kind of view
>> things with Trey right now?
>> Yeah, I mean uh it's nothing's changed.
Like we love Trey and and so you would
just one day at a time. I mean right now
as I said there were just focused on the
draft and I think he and his crew were
just kind of at this point waiting to
see you know what the opportunities are
here or you know potentially elsewhere.
>> Do can I do you have a plan for Jordan
Hancock right now that you know or will
that develop over time as far as safety
or
>> Yeah. I mean, we like versatility.
What's position one? I wouldn't want to
say that yet till we kind of get out
there in the spring. That's probably
something that would declare itself, you
know, more at camp. But I still think
we'll try and make him as versatile as
possible because you never know on game
day. You know, if you're not the
starter, we want you to kind of know
multiple spots.